

Aristotelis Metsinis

Connectivity Engineer

47B Thessalias Street, Halandri, Athens, 15231, Greece http://www.thinkageek.com/metsinis/ | http://www.linkedin.com/in/aristotelismetsinis aristotelis.metsinis@gmail.com | (+30) 6944300173

Profile

High qualified, self-motivated senior Telecommunications and Software engineer with extensive experience in the mobile industry working as a:

- "Connectivity Engineer", being responsible for the administration, maintenance, and support
 of Persado's global Gateway infrastructure, designing and delivering, in a timely manner, the
 messaging interconnections with Persado's clients and partners.
- "Value Added Services" software engineer, being responsible for the entire life-cycle of Vodafone's in-house developed messaging service applications, including the requirements and specifications analysis, design, implementation, integration, quality assurance and software testing as well maintenance, monitoring, optimization and troubleshooting.
- "Cellular Systems" radio engineer, being responsible for the cell design, frequency as well as capacity planning of Vodafone's radio network.

An engineer capable of reliably managing and delivering effective solutions and results on time, working under hard pressure and strict time margins, as part of a team or individually, building trusting relationships with customers and colleagues. A dedicated professional with a solid academic background, equipped with great attention to detail, with excellent interpersonal, analytical thinking and problem solving skills, effectively conveying information verbally and in writing; committed to adapt and succeed in any environment.

Experience

PERSADO – Athens, Greece

07/2013 - Present

Connectivity Engineer

Operations department | Responsible for:

- The contribution to the effective service provision of the technical Operations team.
- The set-up, configuration, testing, deployment and support of Persado's gateways, establishing connectivity between Persado and its clients for the purposes of large-scale digital marketing campaigns.
- The collaboration with several technical teams, delivering the desired connectivity in line with other project requirements.
- Serving as the point of escalation for any connectivity related problems for live projects.
- Participating in troubleshooting sessions with client technical teams.
- Proactively administering Persado's gateways, ensuring the highest level of availability.
- Providing 2nd & 3rd level support.

VODAFONE – Athens, Greece

01/2005 - 06/2013

Associate Senior Data Messaging Services Development Engineer

Southern Europe Technology division, Engineering function, Service Design & Development department, Messaging Solutions group | Responsible for:

• The definition of procedures, ensuring the proper development, integration and monitoring

of new Value Added messaging Services.

- The documentation of service applications.
- The Technical Requirements Specification Reports.
- The set-up, configuration, testing and administration of Vodafone's messaging gateway, establishing connectivity between internal and external Value Added Service applications and Vodafone's SMSC/MMSC platforms.
- The administration of Vodafone's branded messaging services J2EE platform, monitoring its
 performance, upgrading with new service features, retrieving statistical data and performing
 system troubleshooting.
- The entire lifecycle of in-house developed service applications, including the requirements and specifications analysis, design, implementation, integration, quality assurance and software testing as well maintenance, monitoring, optimization and troubleshooting:
 - Real-time service applications written in Java and Perl programming languages, making use of a variety of communication protocols such as HTTP, RPC/XML, SOAP/XML, etc., running on Solaris (Unix) operating system, while exchanging information with a number of diverse systems such as Billing, Provisioning and Data Warehouse platforms as well as Oracle relational databases (via SQL).
 - Web based applications supporting the functionality of the above services, allowing
 access to Marketing end-users and Customer Care agents, displaying statistical data,
 or exporting reports, etc. The underlying programming languages and technologies
 being used extend from HTML, CSS, JavaScript and JQuery to server-side pure
 Servlets and JSPs, running on Apache-Tomcat web-container environment.

VODAFONE - Athens, Greece

09/2000 - 12/2004

Cellular Systems Engineer

Technology division, Engineering function, Radio Systems department, Radio Performance group, Radio planning team | Responsible for the:

- Monitoring of the radio part of the cellular network, taking corrective actions and ensuring network and quality of service key performance indicators.
- Capacity and frequency planning of the radio network.
- Introduction of new GSM (900/1800 MHz), GPRS and UMTS radio functionalities.
- Design of new radio cells and base stations.
- Design and development of the cellular network for "Vodafone Albania".

UNIVERSITY OF ATHENS – Athens, Greece

09/1995 - 09/1996

Microcomputers Laboratory Demonstrator

Mathematics department | Responsible for the:

• Education and practice of undergraduate students in subjects concerning Informatics. Lectures on Pascal and MS-Dos / MS-Windows operating systems and applications.

HELLENIC STATISTICAL AUTHORITY – Athens, Greece

03/1996 - 04/1996

Practice on Statistics

Project in collaboration with the department of Mathematics of the University of Athens:

Collection and statistical analysis of data from the Greek trade area.

HELLENIC AIR FORCE – Greece

04/1999 - 09/2000

Meteorologist

Hellenic National Meteorological Service | Responsible for the:

- Observation, reporting and encoding the weather elements required for the pre-flight weather reports and also the en-route weather radio message.
- Explanation of the procedures used to estimate the subjective elements of the weather report/forecasting (e.g. visibility, weather and cloud type, amounts and height).
- Description of the procedures used to accurately obtain the objective elements of the weather report (e.g. wind speed and direction, pressure and temperature).
- Knowledge acquisition of the various systems, equipment and instruments in use, including their limitations.
- Understanding the need for issuing accurate weather reports, especially in the case of an aircraft incident.
- Decoding civil "METAR" and "SYNOP" weather reports.
- Understanding of air masses, weather fronts and the way clouds are formed.

Skills

- Professional Programming languages: Java, Perl, Python, C/C++, Pascal (Turbo), XML, SQL & PL/SQL, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, JQuery, JSP, PHP, R.
 - Operating Systems & Environments: MS-Windows, Unix (Solaris) & Linux (CentOS).
 - Databases: Oracle.
 - Software packages: Microsoft Office, IntelliJ, Komodo, Eclipse, SQL Navigator, XML Spy, Ultra Edit, Matlab, Notepad++, Wireshark, RStudio.
 - Cellular network planning & management tools: Quantum, VGis (Vodafone Geographical Information System) & OSS (by Ericsson).

Education

UNIVERSITY OF ESSEX – Essex, England

1997 - 1998

Master of Science (MSc.) in "Telecommunication and Information Systems"

Electronic Systems Engineering department | Grade: 76.34%

- Project on "Radio Wave Propagation with Applications on Cellular Mobile Radio Systems". Grade: 90%
- Nortel (Northern Telecom) Prize for the best overall student performance on the MSc. course in "Telecommunication and Information Systems" offered by the Electronic Systems Engineering department of the University of Essex.
- Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council (EPSRC) studentship.

UNIVERSITY OF ESSEX – Essex, England

1996 - 1997

Postgraduate Diploma (Pg. Dip.) in "Communication Systems"

Electronic Systems Engineering department | Grade: 74.20%

Project on "Traffic and Switching in an ATM Network: a Statistical Analysis". Grade: 80%

UNIVERSITY OF ATHENS – Athens, Greece

1991 - 1996

BSc. in "Mathematics"

Mathematics department | Grade: 7.22 / 10

Training
Courses,
Seminars,
Online
Classes

& Conferences

SOFTWARE ENGINEERING

- Coursera.org Kalman Hazins, Adjunct Professor of Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University, "Ruby on Rails: An Introduction" online course, February, 2016. Grade: 98.1%. Project web page: http://www.thinkageek.com/metsinis/ruby on rails.html
- DataCamp Filip Schouwenaars, "Intro to Python for Data Science" online course, December,
 2015.
- Coursera.org Adam Porter, Professor of Computer Science, University of Maryland, "Programming Mobile Applications for Android Handheld Systems # 1" online course, May 6 June 16, 2015. Grade: 100.0%. Project web page: http://www.thinkageek.com/metsinis/programming mobile applications for android handh
 - http://www.thinkageek.com/metsinis/programming_mobile_applications_for_android_handheld_systems.html
- Coursera.org Joe Warren, Professor of Computer Science & Scott Rixner, Professor of Computer Science & John Greiner, Lecturer of Computer Science & Stephen Wong, Lecturer of Computer Science, Rice University, "An Introduction to Interactive Programming in Python" online course, September 15 November 22, 2014. Grade: 100.0% (accomplishment with distinction). Web page of "mini-projects" in "Python": http://www.thinkageek.com/metsinis/interactive programming in python.html
- Sun Microsystems, "Creating Web Services Using Java Technology" training course, Athens, September 20 22, 2010.
- Sun Microsystems, "JavaScript and DOM the Ajax Building Blocks" training course, Athens, July 22 23, 2009.
- Sun Microsystems, "The JavaScript Language and Ajax for Java Developers" training course, Athens, July 16 17 & 20, 2009.
- Oracle, seminar on "Oracle Database 10g: Administration Workshop I", Athens, October 06 10, 2008.
- Oracle, seminar on "Oracle Database 10g: Program with PL/SQL", Athens, June 04 08, 2007.
- Sun Microsystems, "Developing Java Server Faces Components with AJAX" training course, Athens, February 05 06, 2007.
- Sun Microsystems, "Introduction to XML" training course, Athens, January 29 February 01, 2007.
- Sun Microsystems, "Web Component Development with Java Technology" training course, Athens, March 20 24, 2006.
- Hewlett Packard, "Perl Programming" training course, Athens, February 06 09, 2006.
- Sun Microsystems, "Managing XML with the Java Platform" training course, Athens, February 21 25, 2005.
- Oracle, seminar on "Introduction to Oraclegi: SQL", Athens, January 31 February 04, 2005.
- Sun Microsystems, "Shell Programming for System Administrators" training course, Athens, January 24 28, 2005.
- Sun Microsystems, "Java Programming Language" training course, Athens, November 22 26, 2004.

RADIO ENGINEERING

- Wray Castle, "Cell Planning for UMTS Networks" training course, Athens, June 15 16, 2004.
- Siemens, "RC UMR3.0 Operation" training course, Athens, March 22 26, 2004.
- Ericsson Telecom, "GSM Advanced System Technique" training course, Athens, November 17
 21, 2003.
- Ericsson Telecom, "Radio Network Tuning" training course, Athens, June 10 14, 2002.
- Ericsson Telecom, "Radio Network Features" training course, Athens, October 31 November 01, 2001.
- Quotient Communications Ltd, "Quantum™ Cellular Network Planning and Management Tool" specialist training course, Athens, July 2001.

MATHEMATICS & COMPUTER SCIENCE

- Coursera.org Mine Çetinkaya-Rundel, Assistant Professor of the Practice at the Department of Statistical Science, Duke University, "Data Analysis and Statistical Inference" online course, February 17 April 29, 2014. Grade: 84.7% (accomplishment with distinction). "Data Analysis" project report:
 - http://www.thinkageek.com/metsinis/Data Analysis and Statistical Inference.pdf
- DataCamp Mine Çetinkaya-Rundel, Assistant Professor of the Practice at the Department of Statistical Science, Duke University, "Data Analysis and Statistical Inference" online course, April, 2014.
- Coursera.org Yoav Shoham, Professor of Computer Science, Stanford University & Matthew
 O. Jackson, Professor of Economics, Stanford University & Kevin Leyton-Brown, Associate
 Professor of Computer Science, University of British Columbia, "Game Theory" online course,
 January 07 March 10, 2013. Grade: 94.2% (accomplishment with distinction).
- Coursera.org Dan Boneh, Professor of Computer Science, Stanford University, "Cryptography" online course, June 11 August 13, 2012. Grade: 100.0%

TELECOMMUNICATIONS

- Lynda.com Lisa Bock, Assistant Professor of Information Technology, Pennsylvania College of Technology, "Troubleshooting Your Network with Wireshark" online course, April, 2016.
- Ericsson Telecom, "IMS Overview" training course, Athens, March 11, 2009.
- Hellenic Statistical Institute, seminar on "Internet Data Collection and Transmission / e-Communication", Athens, May 09 23, 1996.

PROJECT MANAGEMENT

• Hewlett - Packard, "Project Management Fundamentals" training course, Athens, December 07 - 09, 2009.

METEOROLOGY, ASTRONOMY & PHYSICS

- FutureLearn European Space Agency, "Monitoring Climate from Space" online course, November 30, 2015 January 03, 2016. Grade: 95%
- Mathesis Trachanas Stefanos, Honorary Doctorate of Physics, University of Crete, "Introduction to Quantum Physics" online course, November 16 – December 27, 2015. Grade: 88%

- NATO Advanced Research Workshop, symposium on "Ground Level and Satellite Ozone Observations: Changes in the Mediterranean Region", Athens, October 31 - November 04, 1995.
- University of Athens Ozone Physics and Solar Radiation Research Group, participation in the 2nd international symposium on "Ozone Depletion and Solar Ultraviolet Radiation Impacts on Human Health: A Case Study of the Mediterranean Region", Athens, October 30, 1995.
- Hellenic Astronomical Society, participation in the "2nd Hellenic Astronomical Conference", Thessaloniki, June 29 July 1, 1995.

Publications •

• Metsinis, A., "Cellular Structure of Mobile Networks", Mobile Telephony and Telecom, February 1999, no. 28, pp. 126 - 135.

Languages

English: "First Certificate in English", university of Cambridge, Athens, June 1988.

Activities

- 1987 & '88 Greek swimming champion.
- 1987 88, member of the Greek national swimming team.
- Member of the swimming team of the University of Athens (1991 1996).
- Licensed lifeguard (since 1995).
- 1991 96, BSc. "Mathematics" representative in "undergraduate courses staff/students Liaison Committee" of the department of Mathematics of the university of Athens.
- 1997 98, MSc. "T&IS" representative in "postgraduate courses staff/students Liaison Committee" of the Electronic Systems Engineering department of the university of Essex.
- Festival of Skyros 1993; member of a theatrical group.